RAVI SHANKAR VATS LinkedIn

Gurugram, HR (122101) (India) P: +91-000000000 Mail: ravisvats@gmail.com

Professional Summary

Innovative Software Solution Architect and **Technical Lead** with in-depth understanding of software development and system design illustrated over **8+ years of experience** in similar roles at fast paced startups such as **Delhivery, GoMechanic, Zenarate**.

Skills

Programming Languages: Python, PHP

Frameworks/Libraries: FastAPI, Django, Flask, Pandas

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Redis(cache)

AWS Services: AWS Batch, Lambda, S3, EC2, Cloudwatch, Kafka

GCP: Webhook, Scheduler

Others: Docker, Git, Airflow, Sentry, Grapahana, OKTA, FGA

Testing: Unit test(Pytest), API testing

Front End:HTML, CSS, Bootstrap

Experience

Zenarate (SDE III /Technical Lead)

2/2023 - Present

- Led the architecture design for User Authorization, implementing robust and scalable access control mechanisms, including Fine-Grained Authorization (FGA) for enforcing granular permissions.
- Designed and implemented a Microservices Architecture, successfully migrating a PHP monolith to a modular and scalable system, improving performance and maintainability.
- Implemented Change Data Capture (CDC) in SQL, leveraging event-driven patterns to synchronize data across microservices, enabling real-time updates and analytics.
- Integrated SCIM (System for Cross-domain Identity Management) for seamless user CRUD operations, ensuring enhanced security, data consistency, and interoperability with identity providers like Okta.

 Designed and deployed an event-driven architecture using Kafka, integrating it with AWS Lambda to enable real-time data processing, asynchronous communication, and scalable event handling.

GoMechanic (SDE II)

(5/2022 - 1/2023)

- Writing highly optimised APIs for mobile application keeping in mind the response time and load scalability, updated existing APIs with reduced response time.
- Segregated the existed project from Monolithic to a microservice architecture, with deployment on separate gcp instance using Nginx, Gunicorn, supervisor etc
- Wrote an application on GCP webhook to handle high load.
- Created versioning of APIs in accordance with the version of android application

Delhivery (SDE I) (03/2017-4/2022)

- Developed APIs for functionalities of the app, with testing on both staging and prod environments
- Creating Database Schema with PostgreSQL both for APIs and scripts for CRON jobs running regularly on different servers
- Deployment on AWS Ec2 Instances using CI/CD pipeline like Jenkins and also with Github actions.
- Used S3, Athena, Lambda and other AWS services
- Complete backend support using services like newrelic, grafana, coralogix
- Using github, bitbucket, Azure Devops for project management.

Education

B Tech: Electronics and Communication, 2015(60 %)

12th-60% | 10th-87%

Achievement: - 95.4 Percentile in Cat '15